were nice
okay I'm gonna get all grants in here
um
cool Grant should be heading in here
soon
what's up everyone for popping along
here
uh we're gonna be talking about our
newest paper on rhodiola rosea the
supplement uh we just had this lit
review published you're the legend deal
you're the legend my friend
um this paper publishes the literature
review
um so
this is not an original study so we took
uh you know all the research that's out
there analyze it all and then you know
publish it which is kind of synthesizing
uh what's out there and so Roto Leola is
something that I've been using for a
long time
um I talked about a little bit on my
guest series on Andrew huberman's
platform and uh there's a lot of of
positive stuff nothing's perfect though
so there's some applications and there's
some conflicting evidence and so kind of
the Hope was to continue on this Mission
I've had my entire career which is uh to
it helped disseminate science
communication and get stuff out there so
it's one thing to publish the research
which by the way is open access which
means it's free all of y'all can go
there and read everything Grant Tinsley
who's going to be on here kind of any
second
um
he is the the first author and his
writing style is beautiful he's
incredibly there we go
um
boom there we go
so hopefully I did this correct
okay there he is there's the man there's
Grant
Andy how's it going
good man how are you
I'm doing well
can't see me yet I can see you can you
hear me I can hear you I can see a black
screen and I can hear you so
interesting I don't know what's going on
there uh
maybe you want to pop back off or
anybody else
help us figure out what's going on
because I can see you perfectly
hey I can proceed I can proceed with the
melodious sound of your voice but if you
want I can jump off and jump back on and
see if we can get it yeah if there's
anybody else out there maybe uh
um yeah the dean says that he can see
you so then the world can see you the
world can see you both so we're gonna
roll with what it is I was good I was
just telling the world about how much I
love your writing style
uh um that the paper is is so incredibly
easy and flowing to read you don't have
to have a super technical background and
so I encourage people it's you went out
of your way to pay and to make sure that
this thing is open access so it's not
buying a pay wall
um so not only is it free for people to
get but it's very approachable uh and
easy to read on their end so we would
generally encourage everyone to go read
the whole darn thing
um but we're going to cover a lot of the
stuff um including things like
some of the research that showed no
benefit no fact it's not here Digital
support we really want to just kind of
cover what we uncovered what you
uncovered rather how much to take one to
take it and just a bunch of other stuff
so
um that all sounded like good game plan
to you grant
yeah that sounds great all right
fantastic uh let's super quick
um I'll give the world here who's not
familiar with you a little bit of your
background
um you're a tenure professor at Texas
Tech you've probably got what 150
Publications in the area of sort of
sports and church and human performance
north of 100 haven't hit 150 yet but
something to Aspire to yeah
um I mean just all over the place you've
done a ton of research on intermittent
fasting body composition
um supplementation those are really your
areas of expertise but anything Human
Performance exercise-wise is is in your
wheelhouse um I know that's a very short
synopsis of you but anything else you
got to add there to help people
understand kind of who you are and if
they want to follow more your stuff and
you know what would they what they'd be
getting into
yeah no I think you pretty much got it I
mean primarily I'm an academic
researcher I do teach classes in our PhD
program master's program undergrad
program I do a little bit of Consulting
and other things on the side but the
Lion's Share my work is academic
research so I love this stuff I I
certainly practice what I preach love
slinging some steel out in the garage
gym walking the walk and all of that but
um no yeah happy to be chatting with you
happy to get into this topic and
anything else that comes up all right
great uh one last check here everyone
audio is good can you let us know I
guess in comments I am kind of scrolling
these ones down here
um let us know vein comes out but it
looks good on my end so we're going to
proceed uh I want to ask uh and kind of
tee you up for a bunch of different
things
um people ask some questions earlier on
Twitter
uh and if I if I saw this you actually
just sort of restarted your Twitter
Grant is that right
yeah you know I was away for a few years
uh I did just just to disseminate
research that's a lot of what I do on
Instagram as well is just share research
from our lab
um so I did decide I know there are a
lot of academics and other you know just
health conscious people who are on
um Twitter more so than Instagram to to
locate some of these articles get access
to them and so on
um so I did after a couple year Hiatus
just for practical reasons uh did resume
uh with the retweet about our rhodiola
rosea article so I'll try to share more
regularly on there and then Instagram as
well is where I primarily share our
research yeah great and uh and Grant's a
great follow
um way more active publishes a lot more
than I do um but again uses social media
pretty much for science communication
like I do so you're pretty much gonna
and occasionally some pictures of him
deadlifting in his garage you're gonna
see those you have to show the people
that you walk the walk that's what it's
for you know yeah yeah for sure all
right great thank you for the feedback
everyone looks like the audio video is
awesome so
um Grant what I want to start off with
first is let's cut to the very Chase
here
um I've been an advocate of rhodiola
myself many years I've used it a lot
obviously in the scouring of the
research we found
um some use cases where it maybe has the
most benefit and in other cases where
it's like well maybe he's not doing
anything here the results are mixed so
let's start with the proactive stuff
um in the papers you were able to pull
up what's kind of like the most
charitable case for rhodiola rosea
what's going to have what type of
activities
um does it promote the best uh what what
use case scenario and then we'll kind of
walk our way all the way down to things
that are like maybe
it doesn't work we don't know and then
even if things are like hey there's been
a lot of research on this and it just
doesn't do anything in this area so kind
of just walk us through that big picture
if you uh if you don't mind
yeah I'd be happy to and I'll give some
context so for those who are listening
aren't familiar we were looking at the
effects of rodeo Rodeo rosea
supplementation in humans primarily we
do have a section on a kind of by way of
background on road net research I'm just
talking about some of the potential
mechanisms and the rationale for some of
this human work we were looking at
exercise performance and I would say
exercise relevant outcomes
um so we didn't cover the full spectrum
of everything that road drill has been
studied for because it is very broad but
with that said we did try to approach it
fairly broadly within the realm of
exercise relevant outcome so um
that's actually very important
for this paper we were not looking at
anything in the medical or any other
this is strictly if you take this as a
human is this going to enhance exercise
performance and so yeah thank you for
that because that is a big thing there's
a lot of other reasons why you may use
it or look up other research
um so to give you some numbers
how many papers were included in our
analysis
yeah so for the human trials there were
there were 16 that we located
um and for those who are into research
methodology we didn't approach this as a
formal systematic review but we tried to
use a fairly systematic procedures I
personally like to do that even when I'm
writing a narrative review which I I
like the flexibility
um you have a narrative review to sort
of go where the literature leads and
kind of knit together cohesive dialogue
but we still try to approach this in a
fairly systematic way meaning there are
certain databases we're using there's
certain terms
um we're certainly not cherry picking
anything we're trying to find any
relevant article we can locate and
include that
um so again not formally a systematic
review in terms of how we registered it
and proceeded but we did try to use
systematic procedures rather than just
kind of you know pulling out the the
most exciting studies and talking about
those so if you were to put a number how
many papers do you think
in general have been done in humans on
rhodiola if we counted the other stuff
um
200 is that 7 000 like it's not creatine
it's not tens of thousands it's not
creatine
um I I would be I would be surprised if
it reached the thousands but I would say
certainly in the hundreds uh and I don't
know definitively because we really did
narrow in early on
um focusing on these exercise relevant
outcomes so once we looked at so not
only just exercise uh humans we were
looking at rhodiola Rose and isolation
um so there there may be a time and
place for multi-ingredient supplements
but that certainly limits our ability to
make inferences about rodeola
specifically and so we narrowed it down
to studies using rhodiola rosea in
particular without other
co-supplementation
um so given all those those kind of
criteria we ultimately had 16 trials
with I think it was 363 total
participants that were included kind of
in this overall narrative that that we
crafted okay great so a little bit of
context there if we included you know
the 16 trials this is maybe representing
10 percent at most of the research on
humans and Rhodiola Rose like if there
were like make probably more like one to
two percent of the things so it really
is confined specifically this is a very
big key when people ask things like does
rhodiola work yeah like remember folks
like we're representing one percent
maybe two percent of the total available
research but that's the only way you
could do these things right because we
are really focusing on just does it help
exercise performance so I think we've
qualified that enough unless there's
anything else you've got to say on that
point but I think we can let me jump
into it no yeah I think we're good we're
good to to roll into it so
um yeah so we can start with the the
exercise performance outcomes and
there's lots of nuance there's lots of
caveats we can get into those things if
we want but
um something it's nice when you have
reviewer comments that actually help you
uh you know improve the paper in a
meaningful meaningful way so we do have
I'll say for anyone who wants to see
this kind of in sort of long form if you
look at section four of our paper which
again this is open access it really gets
into the Practical strategy so um we
sort of approached this if you if you're
if you already know you're going to use
rhodiola
um this would be what we would use the
evidence-based way to do this uh again
there are mixed results on some of these
outcomes but um
more plainly
in case somebody just hopped on or
whatever you went out of your way in
section four of the paper specifically
to try to practical application which
covers how much to take what type uh
when to take it do you have to cycle it
every day like all those things is
specifically in the paper already and
it's all open access which means it's
not buying any paywall anywhere in the
world you can go grab that pull that up
read that section and it's going to walk
you through if you want to take rhodiola
we're not saying you maybe should or
shouldn't whatever but if you wanted to
you can go right to that thing so if you
want to skip this entire Instagram live
you're like yo I'm sold how much do I
take when do I take it just go to
section four Grant already wrote it all
up based on the evidence and based on
the literature that that's that's as
direct and plain as we can be there
yes with the minor caveat there there's
some items for example sex differences
where we essentially say the literature
is limited enough that we can't really
put forth a recommendation um the
majority of these trials were in males
there were a couple of mixed sex but
without sex specific analysis this is
just an example
um so we'll say when we think that we
can't actually make a judgment call on
for example
um sex differences or something like
that so there are the practical
applications to the extent we felt like
the literature allowed them at this
point was this actually a great point if
it's not in that section it's because of
what you just said there just wasn't
enough evidence for us to make a
recommendation so if you're like you
forgot x and x no we didn't and we put
everything in there that if there's
papers on it
so that that's the best way to do maybe
um in a follow-up or later we could get
you to espouse on what you personally
think for situations where it's not
covered by the research but you know put
your coaching hat on a little bit but
yeah for now that's in the paper if you
want to know like just base give me the
science what's the science say
um that's already there for you yeah
yeah so getting into to some of the
exercise outcomes
um so I'll say something that's
interesting about this we sort of split
uh generally the exercise outcomes into
categories that maybe won't be a
surprise to anyone but looking at things
more on the endurance uh performance and
capacity into the Spectrum and then on
the more strength and power end of the
spectrum something that I found really
interesting about the literature is the
doses are very different that have been
used
um so ultimately when we get to like the
doses that we might recommend for each
of these it's really based on the
literature but the literature itself has
used very different doses consistently
so on the endurance side relatively
lower doses have been used from say sub
200 milligrams up to I think the higher
ones are around 680 milligrams yeah
exactly yeah and the studies that did
show benefits on the endurance side
typically used about 200 milligrams of
rhodiola rosea or higher most commonly
it was standardized to about one percent
solidricide and about three percent Rose
bins yep and then in the acute setting
typically administered about an hour
before exercise
um so not unanimously beneficial but
when there were benefits seen for things
like cycling time to exhaustion and time
trial performance that's kind of where
we saw it so again about 200 milligrams
of rodeo rosea or higher and uh the one
percent
um cylinder side three percent Rose
events in our pre-exercise
um what's interesting when you look at
the strength and power side again the
full spectrum that we saw studied was
from say sub 200 milligrams up to 680
milligrams or so on the endurance side
there are fewer trials on the strength
and power side but they all used higher
doses so I believe three of the four
main trials we discussed used 1.5 grams
of rhodiola rosea uh and this is
typically through split yeah yes 1500
milligrams yeah so whereas this you know
we're down with that upper upper
um you know dose we saw of around 600 to
700 milligrams on the endurance side
almost all the doses are double that
higher end on the strength and power
side
um some of that may have to do with the
recency some of these trials on uh
resistance exercise outcomes and say
like power production on I'd say a
cycling test like a Wingate test some of
these are newer and maybe like pushing
into higher doses but that was where
personally I thought some of the
research was a little more promising it
is more limited in number but there were
Ben benefits that I was a little bit
more impressed with on the strength and
power side a big caveat here is like
when you look at our paper you'll see
and we try to State this clearly but
you'll see then when we're recommending
um the dose for strength and power
outcomes if you are going to take it
again not saying that you need to but
typically those benefits were seen with
that 1500 milligram per day dose
including 500 milligrams within the hour
pre-exercise so you could look at this
at face value and say like oh you do you
need a much higher dose for strength and
power outcomes and it may look like that
face value but again we try to State it
clearly that's really just because of
what the literature has looked at the
literature has looked at lower doses low
to moderate doses on the endurance end
of the spectrum and then decent amount
higher doses on the strength and power
end of the spectrum yeah which another
way to say that is
I don't know if we saw any papers who've
looked at strength power or hypertrophes
at 300 milligrams
not the studies have looked at it and
found a good work they just they haven't
done it yet so yes the ones that have
tried it have used 1500 Megs or
something like that and you saw some
stuff so it might work at 750. it might
work at 100 I don't know
but that's different than having studied
been studied and shown to not be as
effective
um nobody that I know has done any sort
of global dose curve right 100 200 300
507 Etc up um you didn't see anything
like that even animal models did you for
performing no I think not for
performance I think there are a few
toxicology studies that did that but um
you're exactly right and that's one of
our main future directions you know that
we talked about in there was we need
dosing protocols really on both sides
because we've stuck to high doses on
strength and power we've stuck to low to
moderate doses on the endurance so we
really need those dosing protocols for
all our exercise outcomes because we
really don't know we don't know if that
high of a dose is actually necessary for
strength and power we don't know exactly
where the optimal dose is still on the
endurance end of the spectrum so we do
need really large rigorous dosing
studies for really all exercise outcomes
still to kind of nail down where the
optimal dose would be yeah okay man love
it love it hopefully right everyone's
finding this helpful I I mean I wrote
the paper I'm still finding this how
well you wrote the paper
um
right here though there's a lot in there
so yeah
so hopefully everyone's uh enjoying this
and getting something out of it if you
look at most manufacturers 100
milligrams per capsule is about standard
I know that's what they did with uh in
momentous
um you guys obviously aware of my uh
conflict of interest working with
momentous so I always like to get that
out there um you can get it in a number
of places so it doesn't matter get it
wherever you want if you want to use it
but 100 milligrams is pretty normal and
so people would you know if you want to
take two or three hundred you you know
take two or three capsules of it I don't
really know of many places who make much
lower dose than that but you could
probably find it especially in
multi-ingredient mixes you could find it
at 50 milligrams or something like that
but that that's a standard number so if
you think about that you would have to
take 15 of those pills to get to that
1500 which is probably like outside the
scope of realistic yeah
yeah and the timing was important right
so again it had to be in that one like
well in fact
was there any research I don't think so
there was no papers that used it like
immediately post-exercise like five
minutes something like that right it's
all 45 minutes to 60 minutes prior to
exercise right yes so it would either be
yeah prior to exercise or be chronic
supplementation
um sort of uh either with with no
respect to exercise or chronic
supplementation but still giving it
pre-exercise dose uh and you're exactly
right I should mention on the 1500
milligrams most of those studies only
use this dose for three days followed by
a 500 milligram dose pre-exercise kind
of on the fourth day card exercise
um testing and there were several
studies that were kind of uh you know
they would cite the previous study and
use their protocol a couple are from the
same lab group so it makes sense we're
seeing the similar kind of form of
dosing protocol but this was not taking
1500 milligrams a day in perpetuity this
was a a short it was a cute trial even
though they had a couple days sort of
uploading um so it's even possible that
it was that 500 milligram pre-exercise
dose that was causing some of these
effects
um so yeah certainly things to consider
yeah no that that's a that's a fantastic
Point what we don't have clear evidence
and some of you have asked this
um I am reading the the questions down
there
um but some of you have asked us you
know what do we know about a year-long
five year long ten year long in terms of
exercise performance there's no data on
that whatsoever in fact there's very
limited data on even six weeks eight
weeks that kind of stuff right maybe you
can break that down but
just trying to believe the longest trial
oh sorry what's that I was just gonna
say the overwhelming majority of stuff
you're talking like protocols like you
just talked about two three days of a
loading period and then and a test like
very short term
yes and there are many that were just
single those I think the longest study
was included was 38 days uh you know so
for many of us who who made the
prospective supplement consumers we're
usually looking for something we might
consume longer than uh 38 days so we
definitely need longer term trials uh
there were a few there are a few ones we
considered chronic we kind of had a cut
off of about a week so things under a
week like these three day protocols
single dosing we consider those acute
within the context of list literature in
say longer than about a week as as
chronic but it's not truly chronic
relative to how many consumers would use
these long term yeah and so it's
possible
that this could cut it away so in other
words it's possible uh serving size like
momentous 100 milligrams maybe take that
every day for six weeks and you might
start to see benefit effect it's also
possible it's not anything besides the
acute high dose so smaller dose over
time might do nothing whatsoever like we
in terms of exercise performance we
don't we don't know that it just really
hasn't been studied yeah
and there were say on the strength and
power side this was an untrained
participant so
um you know take a little bit of a grain
of salt if you're exercise trained but
there were studies that were several
weeks long say about a month long
um where they did see some improvements
in actual adaptations in terms of
strength uh Power repetitions to failure
and so on again those with a relatively
high dose
um still of rhodiola
um but but worth considering there were
some chronic trials in there but again
just fairly short-term chronic trials
um what's the longer term trials what's
the highest dosage you saw and did you
see any evidence I can't remember any
of adverse effects in other words like I
don't think there's any
downside we saw I've taken 500
milligrams a day
yes so the the highest dose in a chronic
study is 2400 milligrams for 30 days
that's the study I was just referring to
yeah the caveat is it had a lower
concentration of cylinder side so weighs
0.5
slider side so it's essentially half the
concentration of cylinder side of common
preparations
um some are even higher than that one
percent yeah I believe they also did not
disclose the rose of in concentration if
I remember correctly
um so this is a critical important point
we have this in the application section
section four of the paper
um but ideally you know you certainly
want a supplement that would disclose
the concentration of rosavin and
solidricide those are thought to be two
of the main bioactive compounds however
there are over a hundred bioactive
compounds that can have been identified
from rhodiola rosea um so future
research may even Branch out and say you
know we're standardizing to these two
particular bioactives but there might be
others that end up being you know
equally important or cumulatively
important in concert with each other so
again 2400 milligrams per day for 30
days was the highest we saw here no
there were not safety concerns we have a
short well not sure we have a paragraph
about this in our discussion it was
beyond the scope of the research to
detail like all the mechanisms that
could be involved in this but we cite
some research uh from uh not from these
exercise trials directly though these
also support that just supporting a good
safety record of rhodiola it's been used
for a very long time we discussed that a
little bit too that its history of use
is very long and you know this is common
for some of these herbal compounds where
those been used for hundreds or
thousands of years you know with a a
good safety record from this kind of
collective anecdote but we do also have
some peer-reviewed research supporting
that as well yeah amazing uh and we've
gotten actually a lot of questions
before we logged on about mechanisms I
don't want to do that right now
um you can go read the word can you can
you give a 30-second answer to like
mechanistically this is not a stimulant
like caffeine it's not
um anabolic agent like growth hormone
and like that can you just give people a
very quick understanding of how's would
this plausibly working out mechanisms
but like what's the most plausible
scenario here in which this could
benefit Excellence performance yeah it's
going to be very broad because the
specific mechanisms are not well
characterized but the general idea and
we may get into other outcomes which
will help kind of develop this point but
the general idea is that this is an
adaptogen we included the term adaptogen
in the title that's often why people are
thinking of
um rhodiola but the idea is that the
compound that essentially increases your
ability to resist uh physiological
stress it increases your ability
potentially to maintain homeostasis so
that's really the goal of physiology in
many ways maintaining homeostasis or to
return to homeostasis after you've had
some perturbation to your system so some
stressor that's occurred physiologically
maybe psychologically that's not what we
got into in this paper but that would be
the broad idea is that this is adaptogen
causes you to be able to adapt better to
these stressors but in terms of the
detailed mechanisms we do cite some
works there's a little bit on the
roadside that might inform that a bit in
the context of exercise but overall I
would categorize it still is not very
well characterized partially because of
the very large number of bioactive
compounds that are included in rhodiola
and also give the caveat and primarily
an applied researcher so we certainly
focused on applied exercise and exercise
relevant outcomes here yeah in general I
don't give a about the mechanisms
if it doesn't work right like I don't
care
of course then I start to care but first
I wanted to know is it actually going to
improve performance and then okay let's
start figuring out how it's working but
if it's not doing anything then I don't
really care at all it's fair um you'll
hear the term adaptogen and cortisol
modulator things like that thrown around
so there's actually an interesting
discussion about whether or not this is
a good idea so the the like here we can
compare is cold water
and so for example one of the things we
know are antioxidants similar idea right
you don't necessarily want to blunt
um stress responses if you're trying to
elicit adaptation because that's the
same sort of mechanism but to date I
don't think there's any evidence
although rhodiola will modulate and
return keep you in closer to homeostasis
um modulate meaning like it keeps you
from getting way too high way too low
things like that that said I don't think
there's any evidence but it's not been
studied exhaustively either that it will
blunt long-term adaptations
um any comments I'm really glad you yeah
I'm glad you mentioned that so we do
discuss both in road work and a little
bit in human work there is some support
for antioxidant effects of some of the
rhodiola compounds but we discussed that
issue particularly not just from the you
know are there benefits of this side but
are there detriments because we know
with very high dose antioxidant
supplementation we can compromise not
only molecular signaling but actual
adaptations to exercise so we do address
that we did not see evidence with that
said one of our major future directions
in addition to the dosing is the need
for better like chronic supplementation
protocols that are adequately powered
which means big enough which means
they're expensive but it is what it is
uh trials that would allow this to be
teased out over a longer period of time
because it's within their own
possibility both on the ergogenic or say
ergolytic side that these effects would
take quite a quite a bit of time to
manifest especially if we're looking at
something like body composition or some
aspects of performance that might be
slower developing particularly maybe in
trained individuals I love it man I'm
gonna wrap this up here pretty soon I
feel like we've done a great job I'm
going to give you plenty of time to go
into whatever stuff you want to get into
maybe just really quickly though
they'll also sort of alert if you've got
any questions out there you know fire
them away now because we're gonna I'm
Not Gonna Keep I know it's late for you
and you got kids you probably just put
to bed you want to get to bed and all
that stuff
um I got mine out there this is my one
hour free time per day it tells tells
you how much I think of you Andy that
I'm spending my one hour free time with
you here
oh I know seriously I appreciate it
um any any papers that we uncovered
will you feel like there's clear
evidence it does not work any situation
circumstances either as a clear
detrimental
or
um a clear no effect or or we don't know
yet there so what do we know in terms of
like the downsides
from that perspective
yeah so I would say
it's interesting so we've talked about
exercise performance so far for those of
you who want the details we have we have
other categories of exercise relevant
outcomes what's interesting in in every
category there were at least like some
glimmers of Hope mixed in with studies
showing no benefit at all um so for
example uh the ability of rhodiola to
allow individuals to like exercise at a
lower heart rate for example
um there might be a study or two that
would show this and then you know
several others that didn't same thing
with muscle damage inflammation
um post exercise uh modulation of energy
systems or some interesting rodent
research supporting maybe benefits for
resting glycogen concentrations and
limiting use or kind of delaying
depletion of glycogen during exercise
um some of that hasn't been looked at in
humans but uh yeah antioxidant capacity
lots of these outcomes there'd be a
study or two with some positive effects
and then several studies without any
benefit whatsoever and there's a lot
lots of reasons for this we do have a
table of all the studies which sort of
allows you to kind of find some of these
common features there are a number of
potential explanations for why there
might be discrepancies many of these
studies are relatively small
underpowered we won't talk stats right
now as much as I would like to but some
of these certainly wondered there might
be some meta-analysis that comes out for
some of these outcomes that would
provide some clarity here but again I'd
say it's interesting the breadth of
exercise relevant outcomes where there
were potential benefits is interesting
to me again it was not overwhelming
across the board where for every outcome
there is a benefit but there were enough
in a broad enough category that I think
it generally provides some level of
support for the idea of adaptogen being
kind of you know resistance to stress in
a broad capacity and that's how
adaptogens were you know first defined
to the literature
um so although let's say the the details
are are in the paper there are many
outcomes for which there are primarily
null results uh with glimmers of hope so
uh it's it's something where I think
certainly be within the realm of
um being reasonable if someone wanted to
try this and again that's why we provide
the recommendations we're not saying
definitively everyone should do this but
sort of if you're going to do this
anyways this is what we view as kind of
the best protocol for this everything
from getting a third party tested
supplement uh to knowing the
concentrations of Roosevelt it's
literacide
um to how you approach dosing for
different outcomes all these things
um so we really tried to make this
available as a resource not only to
researchers but to practitioners and
individual consumers as well yeah and I
think you did a great job of writing the
paper where again I really do think any
any random person not in this field not
a scientist could pick that paper up and
read it front to back I'm not saying
it'd be as interested in all the
methodology parts of it or whatnot but I
don't think anyone would really have
that hard of a Time following uh the
writing it's it's very smooth and easy
to read
um several questions pop kind of up uh
about whether or not you and I have ever
tried it as I mentioned before I've used
it a billion times I grabbed it off my
shelf I've got some right here
um again I use momentous and all
um uh conflict of interest disclosure
like one of the main reasons they make
it I kept telling them for so many years
I'm like you've got to make this it's
you know there's good research here
worth making
um again also though you do not need to
take it let me say something there yeah
for anyone who's curious um Angie
exerted zero pressure anyway he was the
the ideal scientist every there's no
study where
um whatever and he's like momentous
won't like this take it out he's
completely objective throughout the
process so just uh as an inside look at
the research process uh you know we
declare any conflicts of interest
because that's that's you know the
honest thing to do the right thing to do
we of course do that
um but I can say from the inside I think
that played absolutely zero role in any
aspect of the paper uh so I think this
paper turned out exactly the same way it
would have whether or not anyone had a
conflict of interest related to rhodiola
so I just wanted wanted to mention that
I myself have used Rodeo as well I
haven't in the last year or two but for
a long time when I started mixing my own
pre-exercise supplements I would obtain
kind of rhodiola and include it with a
number of other ingredients in a
multi-ingredient supplement so I'm
diving into this certainly kind of made
it resurface in my mind I haven't
started taking it again since then but
it's certainly on the list I might have
to cycle off some other things just to
avoid some of the co-supplementation
because of course just that individual
level if you want to know if a
supplement's working it's useful to kind
of test it in isolation uh when possible
yeah as any scientist would right that's
that's the process of Science and hold
everything else constant change one
thing and then see if it does anything
else
um okay man I can go on and on and on I
would love to actually like Beyond
thoroughly enjoying this I think your
discretion is so uh anything else so you
feel like
um
it was super interesting or you just
feel like people would want to know the
answer too they're not going to go read
the paper maybe you can catch them for a
minute or hear anything else that jumped
out I was like I feel like you got to
get out to the world here if this is
only disposal they have this paper
yeah you know I feel like we hit the
high point so muddy the water is too
much again if you if you want more
details on exercise performance
um or the exercise relevant outcomes we
have that we have a big table of the 16
studies we have summaries of each of
them so if you want the details there
they are there
um the main points I wanted to hit I
think we have hit which is really
related to that that section four of the
paper that sort of the Practical
applications uh kind of the so what so
if you're not someone that normally
reads peer-reviewed research but you're
interested in this you could read that
section alone and you should get a fair
look at the outcomes we saw more
benefits for Less benefits for and so on
uh now if you're a researcher I'll give
one plug we do have a decently Hefty
kind of summary in future directions
article so if you're interested in
rhodiola and you're wanting to conduct
studies we do try to set up what we
believe are some of the important
studies related to
um long-term use actual adaptations
exercise the dosing protocols we talked
about again this lack of clarity both on
the strength and power side because
we've sort of only used low the moderate
doses are only used very high doses so
there are a number of kind of
considerations there for maybe the few
researchers on here if you want to
conduct the next study so when we update
this article in a decade we have some
some more good stuff to work on
yo no I mean you gave uh Master students
doctoral students maybe it's a postdocs
man you gave them some layups I can't
basically outlined some of the stuff for
them right there which I think these
would be fantastic projects
um to go and do and and to be really
also clear
um somebody asked me this question sort
of earlier a couple days ago I think
when we published the paper and they
said like I thought you weren't a huge
supporter of uh cortisol modulators uh
I'm not a supporter or unsupporter of
anything and neither are you yeah this
is an interesting topic we feel like
there was enough research out there
to conduct a a review it hadn't been
done yet and so we did it and the
results are whatever they are nothing
supplementation wise is a Panacea
meaning nothing works for everything
um as much as we love creatine and
caffeine and some of the really standard
ones they they don't all work for
everyone they don't work for every
scenario and anyone who would ever try
to convince you that basically any
supplement does so is
um it's probably reason to question
their authenticity and so
um while you and I I think it has
nothing to do with us you just look at
the literature it's pretty clear that
there's some some potential benefits of
rhodiola you could certainly perform at
extremely high level in whatever it is
you're doing exercise without it at all
um but if you were to want to try it for
whatever reason
um I think there's Merit there and there
didn't appear to be much downside
um again within the scope that we saw
there's other considerations maybe
digestive or or hormone or other things
but within our scope
um seem to be a potential and it's
either neutral or potential positive
effects is I think a fair way to
characterize what we found based on the
16 Trials of human exercise performance
that were included in our analysis is
that a fair summary
I think it is a fair summary uh and
you're right you know we haven't tested
rodeo in every other ingredient you
could combine it with
um you know that hasn't been done so
there's certainly certainly some some
questions there uh that remain but
um I was curious Andy if you have any
perspectives from the practitioner side
on when you might implement this or
might not and if that's too big of a
topic you certainly don't need to touch
it but I know you do have a lot of
experience with this and we focus kind
of just on the literature here but now
we have to you know take this literature
and apply it you know in certain
contexts the way yeah maybe it should be
applied yeah no man I've used it up a
bunch um oddly enough this sounds super
weird but we've had a lot of success uh
with rodeola
um as a testosterone aid if you would
um no you could jump through a lot of
speculation there on why I don't
necessarily know why but doing exactly
what you said earlier controlling
everything else adding in rolliola
um we saw a huge benefit many many many
times
there's obviously a testosterone
cortisol ratio if cortisol is extremely
high then that's going to suppress
towards cortisol or a testosterone
that's not important I don't know why it
could be
um
total fluke could be the fact that we're
doing typically lots of other things as
well but
um independent of those things when we
held it constant it's still a pretty big
benefit there
so in general when I typically think
about it um there are other ways to
improve exercise performance if you're
looking for muscular endurance right I'm
going to start with the classics like
we're obviously going with the caffeine
and creatine and potentially a
beta-alanine or a sodium bicarbonate or
you know like something like that that
has a lot more research on it where we
typically you tend to use rhodiola are
people that have maybe a need for
greater adaptogen regulation right so
they are struggling or have other signs
of homeostatic dysfunction and we kind
of want to put them there also people
who tend to respond to it pretty quickly
if
um we're generally the belief that like
if we're not seeing any benefit we don't
like to take supplements like just for
the sake of it so if we're getting a big
response or they can't take beta alanine
or tried it and didn't like it or they
don't respond well to caffeine or when
all those things come off the list then
we start going okay well another way to
get to a similar idea is rhodiola and so
that's typically how we think about but
we're not jumping this over on top of
caffeine creatine you know and of course
all the basics a good training program
good sleep like all that other stuff
this comes way after all of those things
right
no
fantastic yeah great great summer guys
curious to get your perspectives on that
yeah don't kill anything else you got to
get off your chest about our paper here
um if if not then
people who want to follow uh more your
stuff see more of your papers go read
all your research I'm sure you got all
up on a website obviously they can
follow you here again science
communication is pretty much exclusive
to what you do through social media you
just started back on Twitter
um so I can hop and follow there if they
like easier access to the links to the
papers and all that stuff but is there
any other place they can follow along
your lab or the stuff that you're
putting out that stuff because you are
insanely productive
um if you guys are into Human
Performance research man there's just
not many people in the world pushing
more stuff out there than Grant
well thank you I appreciate that I'm
really fortunate to have a great team of
PhD students Master students
undergraduate students collaborators
such as yourself so no primarily if they
if they're a student too
um give them that jam or do they want to
come work in your lab all that stuff
give them the whole spiel
I hesitate to say this I might be
recruiting one PhD student for fall 2024
um frequently adding master of students
undergraduate students I'm out in West
Texas and Lubbock Texas I love it here
some people don't but if you love West
Texas or willing to consider West Texas
it's a great School uh our department is
this is where it is if you love this
stuff man like I went to Central Indiana
for four years yeah uh like you you go
you will find a way to love the area to
do the type of work you're doing and be
involved from your work there's corn
Cotton Fields you know everywhere it
won't distract you from your work you
can you know you can focus but uh no so
yeah Instagram and now Twitter I'll
share our research there I have a
personal website just my name Grant
tinsley.com that has more information
about me my lab some of my other
activities and you can get in touch with
me through social media or or on my
website but um but that's pretty much
all I have to plug nothing nothing too
too crazy
all right you don't got a book out there
no training courses nothing like that
right
uh not yet not yet when I get called up
to the big leagues like you then I might
might start having some of that
no no no sir you're not gonna find me
doing books anymore that's it that's a
wonderful yeah yeah
I'd much rather just honestly like I'd
much rather do science and do cool
projects like this it's just far more
interesting oh yeah
so
um cool we got that uh Grant and I got
another project coming out
um Grant was instrumental in our
intermittent fasting project that paper
is being written right now and so uh
we'll probably have to hop back on when
that thing comes out
um we got some other papers in the Hop
too right some that are in review coming
back tainted supplements one with with
Andrew right yes yes good one Andrew
jagan let up absolutely yeah so you'll
see more Grant we'll be around uh you
know hit them up if you need anything
check out his website other than that
man can't thank you enough for the time
I think this was uh
um this was fun for me man and uh I
don't know if anyone else enjoyed it or
did um if they did maybe we'll consider
doing another one if they let us know
but if not I don't care because I had a
great time hey so yeah we got to chat so
that's great I had a good time too so um
but yeah thanks everyone listening and
great talking with you of course Andy
all right peace out my man awesome take
care
foreign